<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shijian Homepage – OAM</title><link>/tags/oam/</link><description>Recent content in OAM on Shijian Homepage</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/oam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Blog: Introduction</title><link>/blog/2021/05/25/introduction/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2021/05/25/introduction/</guid><description>
&lt;p>An open standard for defining cloud native apps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Focused on application rather than container or orchestrator, Open Application Model [OAM] brings modular, extensible, and portable design for modeling application deployment with higher level yet consistent API.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is the key to enable simple yet robust application delivery across hybrid environments including Kubernetes, cloud, or even IoT devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="1-traditional-way---app-deployment-is-hard">1. Traditional Way - App Deployment is Hard&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Developers spend time on infrastructure details instead of apps - ingress, labels, DNS, etc, and learning how the infrastructure is implemented.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Inextensible - upper layer platform may be introduced, but it&amp;rsquo;s almost certain that the needs of your app will outgrow the capabilities of that platform soon.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Runtime lock-in - app description is tightly coupled with the runtime infrastructure, which heavily impact on how you configure, develop and operate the app across hybrid environments.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="2-the-oam-way---an-app-centric-approach">2. The OAM Way - An App-centric Approach&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Application first - define the app with a self-contained model, where operational behaviors as part of app definition, free of infrastructure here.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Clarity and extensibility - an open standard to modularize platform capabilities into reusable pieces, assemble them into an app deployment per your own needs, fully self-service.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Runtime agnostic - a consistent experience to deploy and operate your apps across on-prem clusters, cloud providers or even edge devices.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Developers think in terms of application architecture, not of infrastructure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="images/introduction.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview-of-the-model">Overview of the Model&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/oam-dev/spec/blob/master/2.overview_and_terminology.md">https://github.com/oam-dev/spec/blob/master/2.overview_and_terminology.md&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This specification proposes a model that defines cloud native applications as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>A cloud native application is a collection of interrelated, but discrete components (services, tasks, workers) that, when coupled with configuration and instantiated in a suitable runtime, together accomplish a unified functional purpose.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In current release, this application model defines the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Components represents a runnable unit, together with a description (schematic).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Workload types identify the different workloads that a component can execute.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Traits are overlays that augment a component with additional operations-specific features. Traits represent operator concerns, not developer/software owner concerns.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Application scopes represent application boundaries by grouping components with common properties or dependencies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An application configuration assembles a set of component instances, their traits, and the application scopes in which they are placed, combined with configuration parameters and metadata.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Thus, an application is a collection of components with a set of operational traits and scoped together into one or more application boundaries.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="see-it-in-action">See it in action&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/oam-dev/kubevela">https://github.com/oam-dev/kubevela&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item></channel></rss>